<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2015 Soft Condensed Matter Physics: Self-Assembly and Active Matter GRC/GRS</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Paul Sokol</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Non-Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports the 2015 Gordon Research Conference and Gordon Research Seminar on "Soft Condensed Matter Physics: Self-Assembly and Active Matter". The award is jointly funded by the CMP, CMMT and BMAT programs in the Division of Materials Research and by the Chemistry Division, both in Math and Physical Sciences, and by the CBET and CMMI programs in Engineering. This Gordon Research Conference will bring together leading scientists from a variety of fields in a collegial atmosphere that supports open discussion to discuss issues at the cutting edge of soft matter physics. This meeting will focus on two topics at the forefront of Soft Condensed Matter Physics: Self-Assembly and Active Matter. Many of the proposed talks are bioinspired. On the one hand, some researchers seek to provide insight into biological function by applying ideas coming from soft matter. On the other hand, other researchers exploit biological principles and phenomena for soft material applications. Topics in self-assembly include biomineralization, virus assembly and assembly of Janus and DNA colloids. Active Matter topics include swimmers, driven colloids, actin and microtubule assembly and tissues. In addition, this conference will be preceded by a Gordon Research Seminar that provides a unique opportunity for young researchers to share in the GRC experience and build informal networks with their peers.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1501169</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Seth</FirstName>
      <LastName>Fraden</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>fraden@brandeis.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/11/2015</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
