<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Career And Research Exploration to Enhance Retention in STEM (CAREERS)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>647705</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Abiodun Ilumoka</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In many situations, the main reason why students do not persist in STEM fields is the lack of knowledge about the comprehensive range of STEM careers available to them once they graduate.  Buena Vista University's multi-disciplinary Career And Research Exploration to Enhance Retention in STEM (CAREERS) program leverages career knowledge in STEM as a novel tool for increased retention of low income, minority, rural (LIMR) undergraduate students in STEM. The project targets STEM majors in biology, biochemistry, chemistry, computer science, environmental science, mathematics, physics and science education. With support from the NSF Scholarships in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (S-STEM) program, CAREERS will provide scholarships and strategic student support to cohorts of Pell-eligible, academically talented students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Evidence suggests that not only do underrepresented minority students have reduced access to role models and mentors but they also experience lower expectations from faculty and lack strong social support networks, all necessary elements for college success. This CAREERS project provides a spectrum of effective interventions such as learning communities, tutoring, mentoring, success programs, and a robust career development plan to enhance underrepresented students' success and retention in STEM fields. Specific activities include seminar-style courses, a career-focused science sampler trip, capstone experiences, directed exploration of science as applied to industry, interdisciplinary research opportunities, internships, and outreach presentations. These will provide critical ingredients for successful STEM career exploration and selection. The project will add to the research literature on ways in which targeted recruitment strategies integrated with curricular, co-curricular, and extracurricular programming around STEM careers shape the career trajectories of LIMR students. CAREERS can potentially provide a model for STEM programs across the country, especially at liberal arts colleges that tend to enroll a high number of students underrepresented in STEM fields.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/04/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1643543</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melinda</FirstName>
<LastName>Coogan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>coogan@bvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Mellmann</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mellmann@bvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Shepherd</LastName>
<EmailAddress>shepherd@bvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gail</FirstName>
<LastName>Hartsock</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hartsock@bvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristy</FirstName>
<LastName>McClellan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mcclellan@bvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Buena Vista University</Name>
<CityName>Storm Lake</CityName>
<ZipCode>505881794</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7127492101</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>610 W 4th St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
