<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Using Validation Theory to Enhance the Recruitment, Retention and Success of Academically Talented Low-Income STEM Students at a Rural Institution.</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>649863</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ron Buckmire</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Nebraska Wesleyan University (NWU) Departments of Biology, Chemistry, Mathematics and Physics will recruit 14 new students who are both academically talented and have unmet financial need to pursue majors in these disciplines. The program will provide them with scholarships, and academic and social support, including orientation, Archway Seminar, faculty advising and mentoring, tutoring and Supplemental Instruction, career exploration, internships, research projects, cohort housing, and retreat and regular cohort meetings, to enable them to graduate in four years and successfully pursue either graduate education or a career in a STEM field. The project will simultaneously develop a deeper understanding and increased knowledge of the factors that affect the recruitment, retention, graduation, and post-graduation success of talented low-income students entering STEM disciplines, often from small rural schools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project includes an in-depth examination of current institutional practices to address the following research questions: 1) How can STEM faculty adjust curricular and pedagogical norms to foster self-efficacy and the development of a science identity in students? 2) From a student perspective, what experiences influence persistence and success in STEM education? The study will contribute to the knowledge regarding the connections between validation, self-efficacy, science identity and culturally responsive pedagogy, and STEM persistence and success, especially in regards to undergraduate students from low-income backgrounds. The results of this inquiry shared with the STEM education community via publications, presentations at professional meetings and conferences, and via the project website and related media. The project's expected impact also includes strengthening recruitment channels that will steer academically talented, financially needy students from many remote rural high schools to STEM careers; spurring economic growth by building a larger, better-prepared STEM workforce for area employers; and strengthening engagement with businesses and professional alumni.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/13/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/13/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1643499</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Garry</FirstName>
<LastName>Duncan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gduncan@nebrwesleyan.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>McKinney</LastName>
<EmailAddress>amckinne@nebrwesleyan.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathaniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Cunningham</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ncunning@nebrwesleyan.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathanael</FirstName>
<LastName>Fackler</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nfackler@nebrwesleyan.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Austin</FirstName>
<LastName>Mohr</LastName>
<EmailAddress>amohr@nebrwesleyan.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Nebraska Wesleyan University</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685042794</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024662371</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Saint Paul Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
