<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Jepson Scholars Program</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>996215</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Crosby</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Mary Washington (UMW) is conducting The Jepson Scholars Program, providing four- year scholarships and integrated support to 20 academically talented students majoring in biology, chemistry, physics, and earth/environmental science.  The Jepson Scholars Program will recruit and serve a diverse low-income student population to develop skills needed for success in STEM graduate programs and careers. The program will therefore help meet the high demand for STEM workers throughout the region including Virginia and Washington, D.C.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This S-STEM project continues best practices of previous projects at UMW while implementing and assessing new activities including: (1) an early, 5-week summer research experience prior to freshman year with strong faculty mentoring; (2) an integrated first-year experience including a STEM-based first-year seminar, advising, and peer-assisted study sessions for gateway science classes; (3) continuing intensive research experiences with faculty mentorship; and (4) robust career preparation through an intensive series of workshops and cohort activities to educate students about STEM career and graduate school opportunities. The impact of these activities on enrollment and retention, graduation, and post-graduate placement rates are being investigated. Formative and summative project evaluation and assessment will employ mixed methods including collection of student data, surveys, interviews, and focus groups.  The intellectual merit of this project is enhanced by the results of this study, which will be used to support sustained programming at UMW and  inform similar institutions of effective practices to support low-income students and improve the numbers, quality, and diversity of STEM graduates.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1643694</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Crowder</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ncrowder@umw.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dianne</FirstName>
<LastName>Baker</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dbaker2@umw.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Whipkey</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cwhipkey@umw.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Kayler</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mkayler@umw.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Mary Washington</Name>
<CityName>Fredericksburg</CityName>
<ZipCode>224015300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5406541269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1301 College Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
