<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Building STEM Pathways</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>999999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Elizabeth Teles</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Because there is a high-need for well-qualified workers in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) fields for the numerous scientific and manufacturing industries in Central New Mexico, this project at the University of New Mexico Valencia Branch (UNM-V) is designed to prepare students for future employment and thus have a significant economic impact on the region as well as the scholarship students and their families. The project will provide funding to enable about 15 academically talented, low-income students per year to attend college full time, graduate with a certificate or associate degree, and find employment in high wage jobs or transfer to four-year research universities. Building on the success of a prior S-STEM award, this project will expand the activities to improve retention, graduation, and transfer rates of students in STEM degree programs. The college will continue to build its Associate of Science in General Science, Pre-Engineering, and Mathematics degrees that prepare students for transfer to four-year institutions such as UNM Main, New Mexico Institute of Mining and Technology, or New Mexico State University while continuing to offer certificates and associate degrees in applied science and information technology. Students attaining AAS degrees will be able to find regional employment or transfer to four year degree programs in technical management or computer science. Since UNM-V is a two-year community college, a Minority Serving Institution and a Hispanic Serving Institution, it is anticipated that the lessons learned from a comprehensive evaluation and research study will provide information regarding the improvement of retention, graduation, and transfer rates for a diverse group of low-income STEM students that can be broadly disseminated and serve as a model for similar institutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will provide mentoring and support services that will build confidence and personal motivation in students. Scholarship recipients will enroll in an Experiential Learning Seminar that is an introduction to a library research and scientific methods course for STEM majors. These students will be tracked by cohorts each semester and compared to a similar group of STEM majors who do not enroll in the course. Through intensive financial and academic student support, such as tutoring, career advisement, the seminar course, non-academic counseling, and faculty mentoring, the program plans to increase the retention and completion rates of participants as well as sustain strong cumulative grade point averages and better prepare students for transfer.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/13/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/13/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1643948</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Miriam</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chavez</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mjchavez@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/13/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Annette</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hatch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ahatch2@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/13/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tracy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Terry</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>tjterry@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/13/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alfonso</FirstName>
      <LastName>Heras-Llanos</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>aheras@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/13/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Melanie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sanchez-Dinwiddie</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>melasanc@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/13/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
      <CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
      <ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
      <StateCode>NM</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1536</Code>
      <Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>8238</Code>
      <Text>DCLS-Hispanic Serving Inst</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
