<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>2017 Micro and Nanoscale Phase Change Heat Transfer: Fundamental Mechanisms to Applications of Phase Change Heat Transfer GRC; Galveston, Texas; January 8-13,2017</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>9600</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07020000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Jose Lage</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The 2017 Micro and Nanoscale Phase Change Heat Transfer: Fundamental Mechanisms to Applications of Phase Change Heat Transfer, to take place in Galveston, TX, on January 8-13, 2017, is organized by the Gordon Research Conferences. This is the second conference on this topic, following the very successful conference held in 2015, and also organized by the Gordon Research Conference. This conference is unique in which it brings together researchers with distinct research backgrounds, who would usually not meet in a single conference, to discuss a topic of common interest, namely the fundamentals of phase-change and its relations to surface structures. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The interplay between form and function in thermal engineering design is a natural evolution to the major advances in materials and manufacturing processes achieved during the previous couple of decades. Particularly in minute (nanometer) scale, the ability to design and build a multitude of complex structures for diverse engineering applications is just now starting to be utilized in relation to thermal design. Our program, in fact, is currently funding a few projects in this theme. This shows a fast critical mass of experts can, and is in the process of being built. The knowledge migration from materials and manufacturing to thermal design requires, however, opportunities for the distinct communities to intertwine. The basic knowledge involved is primarily multidisciplinary, including material science and engineering, chemistry, metallurgy, mechanics, and thermal sciences. This conference provides an essential mechanism for this migration.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>12/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1644770</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Evelyn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wang</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>enwang@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/08/2016</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1406</Code>
      <Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9150</Code>
      <Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
