<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Being Black Isn't Enough - How Variation in Black Political Leadership affects Black Mass Political Behavior</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>18240</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Timothy Nokken</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>General Abstract&lt;br/&gt;This project studies how the ways black politicians show their commitment to political problems in the black community. In particular, it seeks to establish whether the choices in politicians' presentation of self can lead to changes in the behaviors and attitudes of black voters. Despite the well-established findings about representation and black political leadership, little has been done to investigate how black voters' perceptions of black politicians may change depending on the types of political messages adopted by these politicians. This study utilizes original experimental data to identify why some black politicians gain more support than others from black voters. The research is of particular importance because it allows us to assess the political responses of black voters as some black politicians become more professionalized and employ a greater variety of means to appeal to voters. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;This project's aim is to bridge the study of black political leadership with that of descriptive representation to identify the causal mechanisms that produce the particularly high levels of in-group candidate support generally observed among black Americans. It seeks to show when and how varying content of the messages of black political leaders might lead to variation in candidate support among black voters. This study employs two original experimental tests that enhance our understanding of how perceptions of a candidate's connection and commitment to political inclusion of the black community might lead to changes in mass political behavior among black voters. The experimental research design allows the PI to isolate the causal mechanism at work, thereby providing greater explanatory power about how differences within black political leadership and displays of community commitment can change the political behavior and attitudes of black voters. Furthermore, it will also allow greater insight into how black representatives are evaluated by black constituents.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1647365</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Julian</FirstName>
      <LastName>Wamble</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jwamble@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Antoine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Banks</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>abanks12@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/06/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
      <CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>009Y</Code>
      <Text>Political Science DDRIG</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1371</Code>
      <Text>POLITICAL SCIENCE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
