<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I: Wave Carpet Ocean Demonstration</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This STTR Phase 1 project enables the development and validation of a fully operational hydraulic Power Conversion Chain (PCC) designed specifically for an ocean Wave Energy Converter (WEC).  A WEC's PCC is responsible for converting absorbed mechanical power to electrical power.  Ocean wave energy is currently an underutilized resource that has the potential to become an important part of a renewable energy mix providing power up to a third of the US while reducing carbon emissions alongside with wind and solar power.  However, device survivability is a key challenge that has thus far held the wave energy industry back.  This project includes the testing and validation of various hydraulic safety mechanisms, advancing the PCC as part of a broader strategy for WEC survivability. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase 1 project will directly support the development and validation of a Power Conversion Chain (PCC) as part of a larger effort to design, construct, and test a full-scale Wave Energy Converter (WEC) prototype in an ocean deployment.  The PCC will be tested using a hardware-in-the-loop approach, in which a computer simulation of the WEC is coupled directly to the physical PCC elements.  This real-time feedback will allow the PCC's performance to be evaluated for realistic ocean wave climates, and will facilitate rapid testing of critical safety mechanisms using the actual components in a safe laboratory environment.  Results from the tests will be compared with a high-fidelity computer model of the PCC to validated performance.  Once proven, the PCC will be incorporated into a revolutionary WEC design, which offers superior storm survivability and power consistency.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/02/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1648834</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marcus</FirstName>
<LastName>Lehmann</LastName>
<EmailAddress>marcus@calwave.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>M.-Reza</FirstName>
<LastName>Alam</LastName>
<EmailAddress>reza.alam@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Wave Power Technologies, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<ZipCode>947081809</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5105089897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1387 Scenic Ave</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
