<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Diversity, Culture, and Identity in America's Research Universities: Research-Based Initiatives that Promote Shared Discovery and Learning by Students, Faculty, and Staff</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>48500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Myles G. Boylan</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is to support the Reinvention Center's 2016 National Conference, to be held November 14-15. Periodic national conferences hosted by the Reinvention Center are used to showcase a number of undergraduate STEM education advances and also provide a convenient venue for networking officials working to improve the quality of undergraduate STEM education in their universities. The 2016 conference goals are to highlight research on the impact of diversity, culture, and identity on: &lt;br/&gt;1. Undergraduate learning, degree completion, and gaps in patterns of student success across different sub-populations; &lt;br/&gt;2. Possibilities for vertical integration of discovery and learning activities involving faculty, post-docs, graduate students, undergraduates; and &lt;br/&gt;3. Possibilities for horizontal integration of discovery and learning across different administrative divisions in research universities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Viewed as part of the national picture for improving undergraduate STEM education, this project is a highly useful complement to ongoing efforts by the Association of American Universities, the Association of Public and Land Grant Universities, the Association of American Colleges and Universities, and a growing number of regional and national networks of institutions with focused improvement efforts for undergraduate STEM education, such as the Center for the Integration of Research, Teaching and Learning (with 46 members), the University Innovation Alliance (11 public university members), and the Bayview Alliance (with 6 US and 3 Canadian university members).  It contributes to the IUSE: EHR objective of supporting Community Transformation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/26/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1649011</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
<LastName>Lamborn</LastName>
<EmailAddress>alan.lamborn@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
