<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Articulatory and acoustic patterns in phonemic and phonetic nasalization</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>10447</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Joan Maling</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Vowel nasalization lies at the heart of a number of important, widely-attested diachronic and&lt;br/&gt;synchronic phonological processes throughout the world's languages. However, relatively little&lt;br/&gt;is understood about the mapping between the oro-pharyngeal articulatory system and the&lt;br/&gt;acoustics of phonemically nasal and phonetically nasalized vowels compared to their oral&lt;br/&gt;counterparts. This project combines state-of-the-art rt-MRI methods and sophisticated modeling&lt;br/&gt;techniques to solve some persistent problems regarding the synchronic and diachronic behavior&lt;br/&gt;of vowels in Brazilian Portuguese, with wider implications for many other languages with vowel&lt;br/&gt;nasalization.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This dissertation applies advanced methodologies in the collection and analysis of real-time&lt;br/&gt;magnetic resonance imaging (rt-MRI) to study phonemically nasal, phonetically nasalized, and&lt;br/&gt;oral vowels in Brazilian Portuguese. Researchers debate whether nasal vowels in Brazilian&lt;br/&gt;Portuguese are phonemically distinct or are underlyingly two segments (an oral vowel followed&lt;br/&gt;by a nasal consonant). This work will add a different perspective to this debate by constructing&lt;br/&gt;and analyzing a multi-speaker corpus of nasal, phonetically nasalized, and oral vowels.&lt;br/&gt;Analysis focuses on oro-pharyngeal differences in Brazilian Portuguese vowels, as well as&lt;br/&gt;velopharyngeal opening. This work aims to show that underlying oro-pharyngeal shape of oral&lt;br/&gt;vowels and nasalized vowels differs from those of phonemic nasal vowels, suggesting that each&lt;br/&gt;vowel has its own motor plan. This will add to a growing body of literature arguing that nasal&lt;br/&gt;vowels are not merely oral vowels affected by velopharyngeal opening, and that oro-pharyngeal&lt;br/&gt;differences in these vowels contribute to sound change. The project will also involve careful&lt;br/&gt;analysis of the acoustics of Brazilian Portuguese vowels and will extend to modeling the&lt;br/&gt;acoustics that can be drawn from MR images. This study will give more insight into the causes&lt;br/&gt;of diachronic sound change, specifically with regard to the feedback loop between speech&lt;br/&gt;perception and speech articulation.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>03/30/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1651197</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Bradley</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sutton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bsutton@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/30/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Shosted</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rshosted@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/30/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Marissa</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barlaz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>goldrch2@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>03/30/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
      <CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
      <ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Illinois</StateName>
      <StateCode>IL</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>8374</Code>
      <Text>DDRI Linguistics</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1311</Code>
      <Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>SMET</Code>
      <Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
