<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RNA Editing: Biology and Mechanisms of RNA and DNA Modification</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>6975</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Arcady Mushegian</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide support for the 2017 RNA Editing Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) and Gordon Research Conference (GRC) entitled "RNA Editing:  Biology and Mechanisms of RNA and DNA Modification" to be held at Ventura, California on March 11-17, 2017. The GRS is a dedicated forum for student and postdoctoral trainees to present and discuss research with peers before participating in the GRC. The major goal of the RNA Editing GRS/C is exposing trainees to cutting-edge science and providing multiple platforms for discussing research results and emerging ideas with leaders in the field. By learning about the latest advances and cutting-edge technologies, participating trainees and scientists will be inspired to utilize similar experimental approaches to gain new insights into their own RNA and DNA modification systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;RNA and DNA modifications occur in all organisms and influence many biological processes including metabolism, neurological function, and immunity. The 2017 meeting will focus on new advances into the understanding of how RNA and DNA modifications affect the biology of an organism and the molecular machines that are responsible for generating the large repertoire of modifications found in any given organism.  Trainees will all present their research in either an oral or poster format at the GRS. Selection of the trainees to deliver oral presentations will be based on several criteria including scientific excellence, individuals from under-represented areas such as women and minorities, new comers to the field and topic diversity.  Two trainees will be selected by their peers to present at the GRC.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is funded by the Genetic Mechanisms Program in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1653700</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heather</FirstName>
<LastName>Hundley</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hahundle@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
