<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2017 Regenerative Medicine Workshop at Hilton Head, SC</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michele Grimm</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1655376&lt;br/&gt;Guldberg&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NSF has made an award to support travel costs and registration fees for 7 workshop speakers and registration fees for 19 trainees and 5 young faculty members who will attend the three-day Regenerative Medicine Workshop at Hilton Head being held March 1-4, 2017, on Hilton Head Island, SC. The workshop, part of a series that began in 1996, brings together national and international regenerative medicine experts from a variety of engineering and scientific disciplines in a small conference setting to effectively convey knowledge, stimulate new ideas critical to advancing the development of regenerative medicine applications and therapies and promote research collaborations. This year's workshop will focus on the theme of cellular models in regenerative medicine. Conference session topics will include: Cellular therapies for liver disease; Cell-based models for human retinal degenerative diseases; Genome sequencing and epigenomic regulation; Regeneration of pancreatic cells for treating diabetes; Nanoscale approaches for cell regeneration; and Combating muscle degeneration diseases.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1655376</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Guldberg</LastName>
<EmailAddress>robert.guldberg@me.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
