<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Differentiated Citizenship and the Governance of Land and Everyday Life in the Making of a Global City</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>15400</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Antoinette WinklerPrins</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This doctoral dissertation research project investigates the governance of land use and everyday life in the creation of world-class cities, a process predicated on displacement of informally settled residents. This problem holds important insights worldwide in light of rapid urbanization globally accompanied by accelerated slum growth, land enclosures, and rampant civil unrest. The doctoral student will document and explain why and how some forms of informal land-use practices are criminalized while others are institutionally endorsed or practiced by the state, and how such de/criminalization practices shape the differential status of citizenship and rights to the city among the informally settled urban poor. The project examines how government officials, city planners, global policy makers, land developers, local NGOs and residents collectively contribute to urban governance, transforming the city through spatial expansion and land-use practices. Results will be disseminated through publications and reports accessible to academics as well as government officials, city planners, global policy makers, local NGOs, and residents. Local outreach and dissemination is also planned via presentations and workshops, as well as via a subsequent online forum. As a Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement award, this award provides support to enable a promising student to establish a strong independent research career.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project uncovers (1) the logic underscoring the city-government-planning complex regarding differential treatment of slum dwellers, how these rationalities evolved, and the consequences for slum dwellers; (2) the subjectivities and associated practices among slum dwellers relative to various axes of difference (class, caste, gender, religion, occupation, language group and type of land use) to de-homogenize this diverse group of actors; and (3) the various views among agents of the city-government-planning complex regarding displacement to de-homogenize the state, which commonly is approached as a monolithic entity. Methods include a mix of qualitative and quantitative ones, including policy assessment, comparing published land-use plans and actual land-use practices, examination of census data, as well as interviews with residents, NGO workers, and actors at multiple tiers of the city-government-planning complex and collaborative research with slum dwellers. Although this research focuses on Delhi, India to examine how world-class city-making models transform the spatial and socio-economic composition of a city, the project provides new insights regarding issues of social justice in cities worldwide including the United States.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1656180</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Debangana</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bose</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>debangana.bose@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ettlinger</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ettlinger.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Ohio State University</Name>
      <CityName>Columbus</CityName>
      <ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Ohio</StateName>
      <StateCode>OH</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1352</Code>
      <Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1352</Code>
      <Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9179</Code>
      <Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
