<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Tribal College Costa Rica International Research Experience</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>100840</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lura J. Chase</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A goal of the Tribal Colleges and Universities Program (TCUP) is to increase the science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) instructional and research capacities of specific institutions of higher education that serve the Nation's indigenous students. Expanding the research capacity at these institutions expands the opportunities for students to pursue challenging, rewarding careers in STEM fields, provides for research studies in areas that may be locally relevant, and encourages a faculty community to look beyond the traditional classroom for intellectual and professional growth. This project aligns directly with that goal, allowing tribal college students and faculty to engage in international research while developing as a cohort of scientists with share experience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Salish Kootenai College will facilitate the travel for up to sixteen students and up to eight faculty to participate in research experiences at the Organization for Tropical Studies at the Las Cruces Biological Research Station, in Costa Rica.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1657001</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Dupuis</LastName>
<EmailAddress>steve_dupuis@skc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Salish Kootenai College</Name>
<CityName>pablo</CityName>
<ZipCode>598550070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4062754800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P O BOX 70</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1744</Code>
<Text>TRIBAL COLLEGE &amp; UNIVERS PROGR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
