<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Thin Film Cardiac Sensor</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project includes providing an unobtrusive blood volume pulse sensor that can be used for a variety of applications. Through home health monitoring, the proposed sensing product can be potentially improve health outcomes of recently discharged cardiac patients. This will also reduce chances of heart failure after release, which is one of the leading causes for hospital readmission. While application can provide significant benefits to the health community, the proposed product can be used for other services as well. The device can also serve as an unobtrusive means to collect information for personal health, athletic training, etc. The device can also be potentially useful in human-machine systems studies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on a flexible, thin film heart rate sensing array. The device uses quantum dots, which have proven to be an effective functional element for optical microelectromechanical systems (MEMS) devices. The proposed technology will use quantum dots in a MEMS device as a new approach to optical measurement of Blood Volume Pulse. The materials chosen allows the MEMS device to be a thin, flexible film, which will allow it to be easily installed on flat, contoured surfaces such as a phone, computer mouse, or clothing. This contribution to sensing technology will allow Blood Volume Pulse to be measured when users come into physical contact with these items.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/25/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/25/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1658450</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yingzi (Lynn)</FirstName>
<LastName>Lin</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yi.lin@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/25/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
