<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Interdisciplinary Water Science and Engineering</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>439436</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This three year renewal of a Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site Program, Interdisciplinary Water Science and Engineering, at Virginia Tech, offers an interdisciplinary research experience to a diverse cohort of students on projects leading to sustainable management of water resources in an interdisciplinary environment. New features of this renewal program include an international component in India and collaboration of some of the REU scholars with VT RET Site participants. The Site will expand the pool of future researchers in water science who will address one of the National Academy of Engineering (NAE) Grand Challenges, (i.e. provide access to clean water). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;VT will host 10 REU scholars over a 10-week summer program where they will be provided with a high-quality learning environment that: 1) stimulates their scientific curiosity in interdisciplinary water research and motivates them to pursue advanced degrees in water sciences and engineering; 2) trains them to communicate scientific information through research papers, seminars, and presentations; and 3) facilitates their social, intellectual, and professional growth. Twelve faculty mentors from diverse academic disciplines will direct REU scholars research.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/14/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1659495</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Vinod</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lohani</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>vlohani@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/14/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
      <CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
      <ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>VA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1360</Code>
      <Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>116E</Code>
      <Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9178</Code>
      <Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
