<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site:   Keck Geology Consortium: Undergraduate Research Pathways That Broaden and Strengthen the Geosciences</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>169085</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lina C. Patino</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Keck Geology Consortium, comprised of earth science departments at 17 primarily undergraduate institutions, will offer undergraduate research experiences for 10 beginning and 21 advanced students per year. The Consortium endeavors to help students: (1) improve their understanding of the earth through authentic research; (2) develop disciplinary and personal skills needed by professional earth scientists; (3) develop their confidence and identity as scientists through greater understanding of the intellectual and practical work of science; and (4) refine their career plans and prepare them for graduate study using intentionally designed research experiences and mentoring.  Gateway projects designed for first and second year students will consist of a mix of field and laboratory work, exposure to the breadth of the discipline, and to career opportunities in the earth sciences. Advanced Research Program students will participate in a four-week summer project involving a mix of field and laboratory study, followed by an academic year-long project at their home campuses. Both programs include analytical and professional development components designed to help students learn cutting-edge approaches, as well as to develop their professional knowledge and skills. Mentor workshops, curricular materials, and technology are used to support the work of student participants and project mentors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The principal goal of Keck Geology Consortium programs is to broaden the diversity of the geoscience workforce and to prepare students for careers in the geosciences. Undergraduate participants, especially those from underrepresented groups, will be recruited from both Consortium and non-Consortium institutions. The new Gateway Program is designed to make the most of, and further, existing efforts at the Consortium institutions to broaden the participation of underrepresented groups within the geosciences and STEM. With an emphasis on yearlong research experiences, structured research curricula, and mentor training, the Consortium programs provide a distinctive model for undergraduate research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/02/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1659322</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
<LastName>Wirth</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wirth@macalester.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/02/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cameron</FirstName>
<LastName>Davidson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cdavidso@carleton.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/02/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Macalester College</Name>
<CityName>Saint Paul</CityName>
<ZipCode>551051801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6516966000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 Grand Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1575</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
