<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Discoveries in Genomics and Proteomics</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>125188</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08080000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This REU Site award to the Genome Sciences Department at the University of Washington, located in Seattle, WA, will support the training of 10 students for 10 weeks during the summers of 2017- 2019. The program 'Discoveries in Genomics and Proteomics' establishes a direct line of communication between leading genome sciences researchers and undergraduate students, enabling participants to experience the wide range of questions, applications, and career opportunities that are accessible through genomics and proteomics. Research projects span human and model organism genetics, genomics, computational biology, and proteomics. In addition to hands-on research in laboratories of their choice, participants partake in various academic activities, including weekly research talks by faculty, workshops on presentation, ethics, the nature of science and science identify, poster sessions, and a five-week GRE course taught by graduate student volunteers. The program seeks to recruit students from across the United States who belong to underrepresented minority (URM) groups, and students at Heritage University and Shoreline Community College, partner sites in WA. This program accommodates a wide range of students, from those with limited prior exposure to those who are experienced and intent on pursuing STEM degrees. Applications are simple (see webpage); personal statement, recommendations, and transcripts are required. Students receive a generous stipend, roundtrip travel, meals, and housing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is anticipated that a total of 30 students primarily from schools with limited research opportunities, including URM students, will be trained in the program. This program builds confidence and skills in preparation for advanced STEM programs, encourages participation in research conferences, and introduces participants to researchers, including URM researchers, at different stages in their careers to create support networks and foster long-term mentor relationships.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A common web-based assessment tool used by all REU Site programs funded by the Division of Biological Infrastructure will be used to determine the effectiveness of the training program. Students will be tracked after the program in order to determine their career paths. Students will be asked to respond to an automatic email sent via the NSF reporting system. Program information is available at http://www.gs.washington.edu/academics/summer/gssummer/index.htm, or by contacting the PI (Dr. Queitsch at queitsch@u.washington.edu) or the co-PI (Dr. Munn at mmunn@u.washington.edu).</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1659680</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
      <LastName>Queitsch</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>queitsch@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/15/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Maureen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Munn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>mmunn@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/15/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Washington</Name>
      <CityName>Seattle</CityName>
      <ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Washington</StateName>
      <StateCode>WA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1139</Code>
      <Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9250</Code>
      <Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
