<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Biomedical Engineering in Simulations, Imaging, and Modeling (BME-SIM)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>356199</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Biomedical Engineering in Simulations, Imaging, and Modeling (BME-SIM) Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site, at East Carolina University (ECU), will provide high quality research experiences to undergraduate students, specifically targeting women, underrepresented minorities, and students whose home institutions provide limited opportunities for research. The educational goals of this REU will be accomplished through a multidisciplinary approach using simulations, imaging, and modeling as a common thread. The popularity of computational research models has increased due to limited use of human subjects and animals.  Furthermore, as the trend towards personalized medicine spurs the development and refinement of models across scales from cells, to organs, to entire systems, multiscale modeling is becoming integrated into clinical decision support. Exposing REU students to innovative research will increase their awareness about graduate school and ultimately increase the STEM graduate school pipeline. The proposed REU program will also strengthen their STEM career paths and increase student's identities as scientists or engineers, and improve their communication skills. The student research projects have the potential to substantially improve the development of models in biomedical engineering which will reduce reliance on human and animal data, and expedite innovation. These models will have many different applications, for example: calculating loads acting on the human body during movement, simulating tasks that cannot safely be performed by experimental subjects, and simulating blood flow through vessels. Additional benefits from this program include improved connections to faculty at ECU partner institutions. Through the REU program students will be exposed to cutting edge research utilizing advanced computational models with applications in biomedical engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the BME-SIM program is to provide a quality research experience to students, especially those who have limited opportunities for research at their home institution or come from groups underrepresented in science and engineering. At the end of the program students should have a better understanding of how to conduct research, increased awareness of graduate school, clarification and reinforcement of STEM career path, and greater identification as engineer/scientist. Additionally, a new focus of this program will provide training to improve students' communication skills. To achieve these program goals participants will be engaged for longer than the 10 week summer research experience by collaborating with home institution mentors. To ensure a broad applicant pool, student recruitment will begin at ECU partner institutions which include several regional HBCUs and community colleges which serve underrepresented minority, veteran and low-socioeconomic status student populations. Graduates of the program will gain a better understanding of graduate school and be competitive in the graduate school application process increasing diversity in the STEM pipeline.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1659796</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
<LastName>George</LastName>
<EmailAddress>GEORGES@ECU.EDU</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zachary</FirstName>
<LastName>Domire</LastName>
<EmailAddress>domirez@ecu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>East Carolina University</Name>
<CityName>Greenville</CityName>
<ZipCode>278584353</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2523289540</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1360</Code>
<Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
