<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Preparing Leaders in STEM Education for High-Need Populations</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>594586</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Kim</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With funding from the National Science Foundation's Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship program, the Preparing Leaders in STEM Education for High-Need Populations project at Lycoming College will recruit undergraduate majors in biology, chemistry, mathematics, and physics and prepare them to become grade 7-12 biology, chemistry, mathematics, and physics teachers. The project will fund 18 scholarships/stipends over 5 years. In this Noyce Track 1 project, Lycoming College will collaborate with the Williamsport Area School District, Waterdale Environmental Education Center, and Lycoming College alumni teaching STEM subjects in high-need schools. Noyce scholars will be guaranteed one paid summer research experience or internship, with on-campus housing provided. Summer experiences will be developed on an individual basis in conjunction with the college's Center for Enhanced Academic Experiences to ensure an experience and placement that best fits each student's needs and interests.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The foremost goals of this project include preparing grade 7 - 12 biology, chemistry, mathematics, and physics teachers and increasing the number of high-achieving undergraduate STEM majors recruited into a career in the teaching profession. Additionally, the project will serve to create lasting improvements to the Lycoming Secondary Teacher Certificate Program by increasing the expertise of education and STEM faculty preparing students to teach in high-need schools; developing a sustainable structure for student networking with mentors and with experts on teaching economically disadvantaged populations; and increasing understanding of effective teacher certification program components. Evaluation of the Noyce scholarship grant will be accomplished with a mixed-method approach using both formative and summative elements. The framework for evaluation will be focus on scholars' reactions to the training provided, learning, and use of new knowledge and skills, as well as organizational support and change, and secondary student outcomes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1660616</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Hickoff-Cresko</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hickoff@lycoming.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Mahler</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mahler@lycoming.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lycoming College</Name>
<CityName>Williamsport</CityName>
<ZipCode>177015157</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5703214101</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>700 College Place</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
