<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>California Coast Noyce Mathematics Partnership</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>995150</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Richardson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The California Coast Noyce Mathematics Partnership project in the Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program will advance the national need of preparing and retaining qualified mathematics teachers in high-need schools. Through a partnership between California State University Channel Islands (CI) and California State University Monterey Bay (MB), both Hispanic Serving Institutions, this Track 1 Noyce project will support 33 recipients in becoming qualified, certified mathematics teachers prepared to teach in diverse classrooms. The project will provide scholarships at the two campuses to undergraduate mathematics majors, as well as to STEM professionals, seeking a mathematics teaching credential, resulting in the production of 20 scholars at CI and 13 scholars at MB. Project components will entail subject matter preparation, pedagogical preparation, field experiences in diverse school settings coupled with cultural competency preparations, and a range of support mechanisms during both the scholarship funding years and induction years of teaching. Support structures will include (i) development of a strong professional network, including mentoring and induction efforts, (ii) coordination of an annual mini-conference for scholars at both campuses, and (iii) frequent collaboration through social media.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The California Coast Noyce Mathematics Partnership project will provide scholars with relevant cultural and educational experiences, improve scholars' pedagogical content knowledge, and enhance scholars' instructional strategies. Scholars will study curriculum and develop interactive learning activities incorporating modern technologies. The project will include academic language development and extensive networking, debriefing and mentoring, by using a tailored on-line collaboration site that tracks data on interactions, vocabulary, exchanges, etc. Data on recipients' progress and achievement will be collected and analyzed for assessment and improvement purposes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1660521</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivona</FirstName>
<LastName>Grzegorczyk</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Ivona.Grzegorczyk@csuci.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Bleicher</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bob.bleicher@csuci.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hongde</FirstName>
<LastName>Hu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hhu@csumb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joanne</FirstName>
<LastName>Lieberman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jlieberman@csumb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California State University Channel Islands</Name>
<CityName>Camarillo</CityName>
<ZipCode>930128559</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8054373651</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One University Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
