<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Multi-Faceted Approach to Building STEM Teacher Education Capacity Utilizing Near-Peer Tutoring of High School Students</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>74803</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Nixon</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Fontbonne University's Multi-Faceted Approach to Building STEM Teacher Education Capacity Utilizing Near-Peer Tutoring of High School Students is a Capacity Building Project in the Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program that will build capacity for creating a pipeline for underrepresented students to become successful secondary mathematics and biology teachers in high-need school districts. This pipeline will connect Fontbonne University with additional high-need school districts with diverse populations. Fontbonne will also develop relationships and formal agreements with community colleges to increase the pipeline of students from these institutions into Fontbonne.  At Fontbonne University, students will continue their studies in STEM alongside their education bachelor's degree programs. This capacity grant will also increase the achievement of high school students in STEM, specifically students in high-need schools with a large percentage of underrepresented minority students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of this project are to increase the number of area high school students, transfer students, and current Fontbonne University STEM students who choose to pursue careers as secondary mathematics and biology teachers and to improve the preparation of students for success in secondary mathematics and biology licensure. To meet these goals, this project will develop ongoing partnerships with high-need high schools with diverse populations to support mathematics and science education. Specifically, this project will develop a tutoring program to strengthen the recruitment and preparation of underrepresented high school students in STEM. In addition, this project will develop ongoing collaborations with community colleges to support bachelor's degree completion through 2+2 articulation agreements in science and mathematics, develop a coordinated advising system to facilitate clear direction for students seeking secondary STEM licensure, and develop an in-person seminar and online tutoring program based on alignment of the STEM curriculum courses with the required licensure exams to ensure student success on the state teaching licensure exams. These activities will encourage high school, transfer, and current STEM majors at Fontbonne University to consider secondary mathematics and science teaching as a career path. The activities will also facilitate a clear course direction and additional support for students as they seek to complete their STEM education licensure.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1660759</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allison</FirstName>
<LastName>Edwards</LastName>
<EmailAddress>aedwards@fontbonne.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gale</FirstName>
<LastName>Rice</LastName>
<EmailAddress>grice@fontbonne.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Weyhaupt</LastName>
<EmailAddress>aweyhaupt@fontbonne.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Fontbonne University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631053098</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3148894510</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6800 Wydown Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
