<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>U.S. Young Scientists at the 2017 URSI GASS</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>48820</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Glen Langston</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award to the National Academy of Sciences will support 30 early career scientists to attend the International Union of Radio Science's General Assembly and Scientific Symposium (URSI GASS), to be held in Montreal, Canada. The triennial GASS is the most important meeting associated with URSI.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award enables participation of early career U.S. scientists at the URSI GASS, thereby allowing the United States to actively contribute to the scientific union at its largest international meeting.  Both URSI and the U.S. National Committee for URSI (USNC-URSI) strongly support the involvement of young scientists in the GASS. The program of U.S. young scientist travel fellowships to the URSI GASS will allow early career researchers to present their research in an international setting, hear about new areas of radio science research, gain familiarity with the URSI Commission structure, and build a network of international contacts.  The fellows will be exposed to the policy aspects of their field and learn how major decisions that affect their field are made.  They also will be encouraged to enter the International Student Paper competition and to engage in URSI Commission meetings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The scientists and students supported by this award will enhance their education and their professional development.  Interactions with colleagues from both the U.S. and other countries will help foster new collaborations and the development of new networks, ultimately resulting in new scientific research that advances the field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1664371</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Bailey</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kbailey@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ana</FirstName>
<LastName>Ferreras</LastName>
<EmailAddress>aferreras@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1219</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL PROGRAMS IN ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
